A Finding Aid to the John McLaughlin papers, 1922-1979 in the Archives of American Art AAA.mclajohn
Archives of American Art
John McLaughlin papers
bulk 1936-1976
1922-1979
AAA.mclajohn
Archives of American Art
3.3 Linear feet
The papers of Southern California art dealer and abstract painter John McLaughlin measure 3.3 linear feet and date from 1922 to 1979. The collection documents John McLaughlin's personal life and career through biographical material, correspondence, writings, Tamarind Lithography fellowship files, scattered personal business records, printed materials, artwork, and photographic material.
McLaughlin, John, 1898-1976
Arrangement note
This collection is arranged as 8 series.
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1942-circa 1969 (0.1 linear feet; Box 1)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1936-1976 (0.7 linear feet; Box 1)
Series 3: Writings and Notes, circa 1934-1976 (0.7 linear feet; Box 1-2)
Series 4: Tamarind Lithography Fellowship Files, 1958-1970 (0.2 linear feet; Box 2)
Series 5: Personal Business Records, circa 1938-1974 (0.2 linear feet; Box 2)
Series 6: Printed Material, 1932-1979 (1.5 linear feet; Box 2-4)
Series 7: Artwork, circa 1958 (0.1 linear feet; Box 3-4)
Series 8: Photographic Material, 1922-1979 (0.2 linear feet; Box 3)
Biographical/Historical note
John Dwyer McLaughlin (1898-1976) was best known as one of the leading Los Angeles "hard-edge" geometric abstractionist painters and one of the artists featured in the seminal 1959 exhibition "Four Abstract Classicists" curated by Jules Langsner. McLaughlin was also a dealer of Japanese art prints.
McLaughlin was born and educated in Massachusetts. He served in the United States Navy during World War I from 1917-1921 and married Florence Emerson in 1928. McLaughlin began painting around 1932 with no formal training. In 1935, the couple moved to Japan and lived for several years before moving back to Boston, where they opened The Tokaido, Inc., a Japanese art print gallery. From this time up to the beginning of World War II, McLaughlin worked primarily as a print dealer, without huge success. During World War II, he served as a language intelligence officer in the Marines, primarily because of his knowledge of Japanese.
After the war, McLaughlin and his wife settled in Dana Point, California, where he began painting in earnest, gaining some early local successes. His painting, Hope Deferred was awarded first prize for oil painting in the 1948 San Diego Art Guild Annual. He became associated with the Felix Landau Gallery in Los Angeles and was one of four painters included in the historic 1959 "Four Abstract Classicists" exhibition at the Los Angeles County Museum of Art organized by critic Jules Langsner which also featured the work of Frederick Hammersley, Lorser Feitelson, and Karl Benjamin. The phrase "hard-edge painting" was first used in association with this exhibition as a description of a unique California style of geometric abstractionist painting.
Throughout the 1960s and 1970s McLaughlin exhibited widely and became a mentor for many younger Los Angeles area reductive painters. He was widely admired for his integrity and independent position regarding the art market. John McLaughlin died in Dana Point, California in 1976 at the age of 77.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center. Contact Reference Services for more information.
Existence and Location of Copies note
Portions of the collection are available on 35 mm microfilm reels 1410-1413 at Archives of American Art offices, and through interlibrary loan. Researchers should note that the order of the microfilm does not reflect the current arrangement of the papers.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The John McLaughlin papers were donated to the Archives of American Art in multiple installments. John McLaughlin donated material in 1973 and his widow Florence McLaughlin donated material in 1976. Additional papers were donated by the artist's nephew John McLaughlin in 1998 and 1999.
Related Archival Materials note
The Archives of American Art also holds an oral history interview of John D. McLaughlin conducted July 23, 1974, by Paul J. Karlstrom.
Scope and Contents note
The papers of Southern California art dealer and abstract painter John McLaughlin measure 3.3 linear feet and date from 1922 to 1979. The collection documents John McLaughlin's personal life and career through biographical material, correspondence, writings, Tamarind Lithography fellowship files, scattered personal business records, printed materials, artwork, and photographic material.
Biographical material includes McLaughlin's military service records, art awards, and resumes. Correspondence is with friends, artists, museums, and galleries. Notable correspondents include Eugene Anderson, Karl Benjamin, Frederick Hammersley, Jules Langsner, Stanton Macdonald-Wright, Ad Reinhardt, and others. Writings and notes include several artist statements, lectures, notes, and lists and descriptions of paintings, some in the form of hand drawn sketches. Users will find McLaughlin's ideas about his work and aesthetics are referenced in much of the correspondence and writings. Some of the letters also document the evolution of the 1959 "Four Abstract Classicists" exhibition, particularly correspondence with Karl Benjamin, Peter Selz, and Jules Langsner. There are also writings about McLaughlin by others, including Jules Langsner. The Tamarind Lithography fellowship files consists of the letter of appointment, printed material, and profiles for fellow artists at the workshop.
Personal business records include assorted legal and financial papers, such as contracts with galleries, art loan agreements, consignment records, and art shipment expenses. There are business papers about McLaughlin's Japanese print gallery, The Tokaido, Inc. Printed material consists of exhibition catalogs for McLaughlin's shows at the Andre Emmerich Gallery, Felix Landau Gallery, a retrospective at the Corcoran Gallery of Art in 1968, and the seminal 1959 "Four Abstract Classicists" in Los Angeles, among others. Also found are exhibition announcements, news clippings, and press releases. Artwork includes a few paintings and collages. Photographs, negatives, and slides are of McLaughlin, including one portrait by John Waggaman), artwork, and exhibition installations. There is one album of photographs from a 1963 retrospective exhibition at the Pasadena Art Museum.
Anderson, Eugene Newton; André Emmerich Gallery; Benjamin, Karl; Corcoran Gallery of Art.; Felix Landau Gallery; Hammersley, Frederick, 1919-2009; Langsner, Jules, 1911-1967; Macdonald-Wright, Stanton, 1890-1973; McLaughlin, John, 1898-1976 -- Photographs; Pasadena Art Museum.; Reinhardt, Ad, 1913-1967; Salz, Peter; Tamarind Lithography Workshop.; Art dealers--California; Art, Modern--California--Los Angeles; Collages; Painters--California; Painting, Abstract--California--Exhibitions; Paintings; Photographs; Prints, Japanese; Sketches
- Biographical Material, 1942-circa 1969; Series 1; 0.1 Linear feet Box 1
  Arrangement note
  This series is arranged chronologically.
  Scope and Contents note
  Biographical material includes military service records from World War II, scattered art fair awards, business cards, selected bibliographies, short artist biographies, and curriculum vitae.
  - Military Service Records, 1942-1945 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Military Service Records, 1945-1947 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Art Fair Awards, 1947-1950 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Assorted Business Cards, 1949-1975 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Selected Bibliography, circa 1968 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Short Artist Biographies, circa 1969 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Curriculum Vitae, circa 1969 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Correspondence, 1936-1976; Series 2; 0.7 Linear feet Box 1
  This series is arranged chronologically. Undated correspondence and McLaughlin's drafts of outgoing correspondence are grouped together toward the end of the series.
  Correspondence consists of personal and professional correspondence between John McLaughlin and friends, colleagues, fellow artists, museums directors, and galleries. Included are letters from the U.S. War Department during McLaughlin's military service, with collectors and galleries about selling his Japanese art prints, and letters about organizing and participating in exhibitions, including the 1959 "Four Abstract Classicists" exhibition. Many of the letters outline McLaughlin's thoughts on his work and aesthetics. Notable correspondents include Eugene Anderson, Karl Benjamin, Frederick Hammersley, Jules Langsner, Stanton Macdonald-Wright, Ad Reinhardt, and others.
  - Correspondence, 1936-1943 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1944-1945 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1947 January-May (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1947 June-August (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1947 September-December (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, 1950-1951 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, 1952-1954 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, 1955-1956 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence, 1959 February-April (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence, 1959 May (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence, 1959 June-December (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence, 1960 January-August (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence, 1960 September-December (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Correspondence, 1961 February-August (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Correspondence, 1961 September (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Correspondence, 1961 October-December (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Correspondence, 1962 February-May (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Correspondence, 1962 June-December (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Correspondence, 1963 January-March (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Correspondence, 1963 April-August (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Correspondence, 1963 September-December (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Correspondence, 1964 January-September (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Correspondence, 1964 October-December (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Correspondence, 1965 January-June (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Correspondence, 1965 July (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Correspondence, 1965 August-December (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Correspondence, 1966 January-August (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Correspondence, 1966 September-December (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Correspondence, 1967 January-February (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Correspondence, 1967 March-December (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Correspondence, 1968 January-May (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Correspondence, 1968 June (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Correspondence, 1968 July-August (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Correspondence, 1968 September-December (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Correspondence, 1969 January-March (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Correspondence, 1969 April-June (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Correspondence, 1969 July-December (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Correspondence, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Correspondence, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Correspondence, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Correspondence, 1973 January-August (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Correspondence, 1973 September-December (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Correspondence, 1974 January-April (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Correspondence, 1974 May-November (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Correspondence, 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Undated Correspondence, circa 1936-1976 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Undated Correspondence, circa 1936-1976 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Undated Correspondence, circa 1936-1976 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Undated Correspondence, circa 1936-1976 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Undated Correspondence, circa 1936-1976 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Drafts of Outgoing Correspondence, circa 1936-1976 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Drafts of Outgoing Correspondence, circa 1936-1976 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Drafts of Outgoing Correspondence, circa 1936-1976 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Drafts of Outgoing Correspondence, circa 1936-1976 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Drafts of Outgoing Correspondence, circa 1936-1976 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Drafts of Outgoing Correspondence, circa 1936-1976 (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Drafts of Outgoing Correspondence, circa 1936-1976 (Box 1, Folder 68)
- Writings and Notes, circa 1934-1976; Series 3; 0.7 Linear feet Box 1-2
  The materials in this series are grouped together by document type, such as artist statements, lectures, and notes, then organized chronologically within each grouping. Writings by others are grouped together at the end of the series.
  Writings and notes include typescript and handwritten drafts of artist statements and lectures, in addition to notes and hand drawn lists and descriptions of paintings. The lists and descriptions of paintings are handwritten inventories and notes that include the medium and dimensions of paintings along with small sketches that have annotations about the colors. The bulk of the material in the series is comprised of McLaughlin's writings in addition to a few drafts written by others.
  - Artist Statements, circa 1936-1976 (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Artist Statements, circa 1936-1976 (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Artist Statements, 1964-1970 (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - Art Lecture Draft, circa 1934-1974 (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - Art Lecture Draft, circa 1936-1976 (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - Art Lecture Draft, circa 1936-1976 (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - Art Lecture Draft, circa 1936-1976 (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - Art Lecture Draft, circa 1936-1976 (Box 1, Folder 76)
  - Art Lecture Draft, circa 1936-1976 (Box 1, Folder 77)
  - Notes, circa 1936-1976 (Box 1, Folder 78)
  - Notes, circa 1936-1976 (Box 1, Folder 79)
  - Notes, circa 1936-1976 (Box 1, Folder 80)
  - Notes, circa 1936-1976 (Box 1, Folder 81)
  - Notes, circa 1936-1976 (Box 1, Folder 82)
  - Notes, circa 1936-1976 (Box 1, Folder 83)
  - Exhibition Review Draft, circa 1950 (Box 1, Folder 84)
  - Handwritten List of Exhibitions, circa 1968 (Box 1, Folder 85)
  - Hand Drawn List of Paintings, circa 1965 (Box 1, Folder 86)
  - Hand Drawn List of Paintings, circa 1965 (Box 1, Folder 87)
  - Hand Drawn Descriptions of Paintings, circa 1955 (Box 1, Folder 88)
  - Hand Drawn Descriptions of Paintings, circa 1955 (Box 1, Folder 89)
  - Hand Drawn Descriptions of Paintings, circa 1965 (Box 1, Folder 90)
  - Hand Drawn Descriptions of Paintings, circa 1965 (Box 1, Folder 91)
  - Jules Langsner Writing About John McLaughlin, circa 1936-1976 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - John Coplans Writing About John McLaughlin, circa 1936-1976 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Exhibition Reviews by Others, circa 1950-1975 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Script for Television Show Featuring John McLaughlin, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Exhibition Catalog Introduction by James Harithas, circa 1968 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Tamarind Lithography Fellowship Files, 1958-1970; Series 4; 0.2 Linear feet Box 2
  The materials in this series are grouped together by type, then organized chronologically within each grouping.
  The Tamarind Lithography fellowship files consists of the letter of appointment, assorted printed material such as brochures and press releases, and artist profiles and photographs for other recipients of the fellowship at the Tamarind Lithography Workshop.
  - Appointment Letter, 1962-1963 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Printed Material, 1958-1966 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Printed Material, 1960-1965 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Printed Material, circa 1965 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Printed Material, 1966-1970 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Artist Profiles and Photographs, 1960-1970 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Artist Profiles and Photographs, 1960-1970 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Personal Business Records, circa 1938-1974; Series 5; 0.2 Linear feet Box 2
  This series is arranged by type of materials, then organized chronologically within each grouping.
  Personal business records include assorted legal and financial papers. Legal material consists of a few estate papers and contracts agreeing to gallery representation. There are business papers, such as sales and inventory notes, concerning McLaughlin's Japanese print gallery, The Tokaido, Inc. Also included are art loan agreements, consignment records, and bills and receipts for art shipment expenses.
  - The Tokaido Inventory and Sales Notes, circa 1938 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - The Tokaido Sales and Inventory, circa 1938 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - The Tokaido Sales and Inventory Notes, circa 1938 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - The Tokaido Employment Record, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - The Tokaido Sales, Consignment, and Shipping Forms, 1941-1962 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Ruth Eaton Peabody Estate Paper, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Florence McLaughlin Legal and Financial Forms, 1950-1957 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Art Consignment Forms, 1952-1971 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Art Inventory and Sales Records, circa 1950-1973 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Art Sales Records, 1959-1974 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Art Shipment Costs, 1961-1974 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Art Shipment Costs, 1968-1973 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Art Loan Agreements, 1967-1974 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Art Loan Agreements, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Art Loan Agreements, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Art Gift Agreement, circa 1971 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Contract with Andre Emmerich Gallery, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Miscellaneous Legal Forms, 1961-1969 (Box 2, Folder 30)
- Printed Material, 1932-1979; Series 6; 1.5 Linear feet Box 2-4
  This series is arranged by type of material, then organized chronologically within each grouping.
  Printed material consists of exhibition catalogs for McLaughlin's group and solo shows, exhibition announcements, magazine and newspaper clippings, brochures, press releases, and miscellaneous materials.
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1947-1949 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1950-1952 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1953-1956 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1957-1958 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1959-1961 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1962-1963 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1964-1967 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1967-1969 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1969-1970 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    Oversized material housed in Box 4, Folder 1.
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1971-1973 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1974-1975 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Undated Exhibition Catalogs, circa 1950-1976 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Exhibition Announcements, 1940-1959 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Exhibition Announcements, 1960-1969 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Exhibition Announcements, 1970-circa 1974 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Undated Exhibition Announcements, 1940-1976 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Magazine Clippings, circa 1950-circa 1970 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    Oversized material housed in Box 4, Folder 2.
  - Magazine Clippings, circa 1950-circa 1970 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    Oversized material housed in Box 4, Folder 3.
  - Magazine Clippings, circa 1950-circa 1970 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - News Clippings, 1943-1952 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - News Clippings, 1953-1961 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - News Clippings, 1962-1963 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - News Clippings, 1964-1967 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - News Clippings, 1968-1976 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Undated News Clippings, circa 1950-1976 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Science and Health with a Key to the Scriptures, 1932 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Journal: The Los Angeles Institute of Contemporary Art, No. 5, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Brochures, circa 1950-circa 1970 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Press Releases, 1955-1968 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Museum Bulletins and Events Calendars, 1958-1976 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Material, 1939-1976 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Oversized Exhibition Catalog from Box 2, Folder 39, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Oversized Magazine Clippings from Box 3, Folder 8, circa 1950-circa 1970 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Oversized Magazine Clippings from Box 3, Folder 9, circa 1950-circa 1970 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Artwork, circa 1958; Series 7; 0.1 Linear feet Box 3-4
  Artwork consists of 1 folder with a few small paintings along with oversize collages that might have served as composition models for full-scale paintings.
  - Artwork, circa 1958 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    Oversized material housed in Box 4, Folder 4.
  - Oversized Artwork from Box 3, Folder 23, circa 1958 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Photographic Material, 1922-1979; Series 8; 0.2 Linear feet Box 3
  The photographs are arranged by subject, then organized chronologically within each grouping.
  Photographic material includes photographs and negatives, as well as a few slides. There is one album of photographs from a retrospective exhibition of McLaughlin's work at the Pasadena Art Museum. There are some personal photographs and portraits of McLaughlin, but the bulk of the series consists of black & white photographs of his paintings and exhibition installation.
  - Photograph Album of Retrospective Exhibition, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Personal Photographs, 1922-1959 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Portraits of John McLaughlin, circa 1959-circa 1968 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Dana Point Studio, circa 1974 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Unidentified Gallery, circa 1950-circa 1970 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Photographs of Artwork, circa 1948-circa 1968 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Photographs of Artwork, circa 1949-1976 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Photographs of Artwork, circa 1950-1966 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Photographs of Artwork, circa 1950-1976 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Photographs of Artwork, circa 1950-1976 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Photographs of Artwork, circa 1950-1976 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Installation Photographs, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Installation Photographs, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Installation Photographs, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Installation Photographs, circa 1950-circa 1970 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Photographs Used in Journal Vol. 20, No. 4, circa 1950-1973 (Box 3, Folder 39)